<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two discourses 1. of baptisme, its institution, and efficacy upon all believers. 2. Of prayer ex tempore, or by pretence of the spirit. / By Jer: Taylor D.D.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E683_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863585</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115793</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E683[15], 247:E683[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two discourses 1. of baptisme, its institution, and efficacy upon all believers. 2. Of prayer ex tempore, or by pretence of the spirit. / By Jer: Taylor D.D.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60; 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Flesher for R. Royston, at the Angel in Ivy-Lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIII. [1653 i.e. 1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "baptisme, .. believers." and "prayer .. spirit." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>A reissue of "A discourse concerning prayer ex tempore" (Wing T313), and either the 1652 or 1653 edition of "A discourse of baptisme" (Wing T315 or T316), with added general title page and conjugate blank, and with separate title pages cancelled. In the 1652 edition of "A discourse of baptisme" p. 1 is signed "B"; in the 1653 edition it is signed "A3".</note>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy 3 December 1652.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb 3d"; the final 'I' in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears on UMI microfilm (Thomason Tracts), reels 105 (part 2 only) and 247.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115793:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO DISCOVRSES
<list>
                  <item>1. Of BAPTISME, Its Inſtitution, and Efficacy upon all Believers.</item>
                  <item>2. Of PRAYER <hi>Ex tempore,</hi> OR By pretence of the SPIRIT.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By JER: TAYLOR D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 14.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>And the ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets.</p>
               <p>For God is not the Authour of confuſion, but of peace, as in all Churches of the Saints.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Fleſher</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Ivy-Lane. MDCLIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115793:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115793:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe concerning PRAYER <hi>Ex tempore,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have read over this Book which the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines is pleaſed to call <hi>The Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for Prayer;</hi> I confeſſe I came to it with much expectation, and was in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure confident I ſhould have found it an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and unblameable modell of Devotion, free from all thoſe objections which men of their own perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had obtruded againſt the publike Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> or at leaſt, it ſhould have been compoſed with ſo much artifice and fineneſſe, that it might have been to all the world an Argument of their learning and excellency of ſpirit, if not of the goodneſſe and integrity of their Religion and purpoſes. I ſhall give no other character of the whole, but that the publike diſreliſh which I finde amongſt perſons of great piety, of all qualities, not only of great, but even of ordinary underſtandings, is to, me ſome argument that it lies ſo open to the objections even of common ſpirits, that the Compilers of it did intend more to prevaile by the ſucceſſe of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, then the ſtrength of reaſon, and the proper grounds of perſwaſion, which yet moſt wiſe and good men believe to be the more Chriſtian way of the two. But Sir, you have engaged me to ſay ſomething in particular to ſatisfie your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. In which alſo I deſire I may reſerve a leave to my ſelf to conceal much, if I may in little doe you ſatisfaction.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115793:3"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>2</label> I ſhall therefore decline to ſpeak of the Efficient canſe of this Directory, and not quarrell at it that is was compoſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lawes both of <hi>England</hi> and all Chriſtendome. If the thing were good and pious, I ſhould learn to ſubmit to the impoſition, and never quarrell at the incompetency of his authority that engaged me to doe pious and holy things. And it may be when I am a little more uſed to it, I ſhall not wonder at a Synod, in which not one Biſhop ſits (in the capacity of a Biſhop) though I am moſt certain this is the firſt example in <hi>England,</hi> ſince it was firſt Chriſtned. But for preſent it ſeemes ſomething hard to digeſt it, becauſe I know ſo well that all Aſſemblies of the Church have admitted Prieſts to conſultation and diſpute, but never to authority and deciſion, till the Pope enlarging the phylacteries of the Archimandrites and Abbots, did ſometimes by way of priviledge and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation give to ſome of them deciſive voyces in publike Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. But this was one of the things in which he did inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and invade againſt the publike reſolutions of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, though he durſt not doe it often, and when he did it, it was in very ſmall and inconſiderate numbers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>3</label> I ſaid I would not meddle with the Efficient, and I cannot meddle with the Finall cauſe, nor gueſſe at any other ends and purpoſes of theirs then at what they publiquely profeſſe, which is the abolition and deſtruction of the Book of Common-Prayer; which great change, becauſe they are pleaſed to call Reformation, I am content in charity to believe they think it ſo, and that they have <hi>Zelum Dei,</hi> but whether <hi>ſecundum ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> according to knowledge or no, muſt be judged by them who conſider the matter and the forme.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>4</label> But becauſe the matter is of ſo great variety and minute conſideration, every part whereof would require as much ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny as I purpoſe to beſtow upon the whole, I have for the preſent choſen to conſider only the form of it; and becauſe it pretends againſt the form of ſet Lyturgy and that <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> forms doe ſucceed in room of the eſtabliſhed and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined ſervices, I ſhall give you my judgement of it, without any ſharpneſſe or bitterneſſe of ſpirit, for I am reſolved not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115793:3"/>to be angry with any man of another perſwaſion, as knowing that I differ juſt as much from them as they doe from me.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>5</label> And firſt, I conſider that the true ſtate of the Queſtion is only this, Whether it is better to pray to God with conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or without? whether is the wiſer man of the two, hee who thinks, and deliberates what to ſay, or he that utters his mind as faſt as it comes? Whether is the better man, he who out of reverence to God is moſt carefull and curious that he offend not in his tongue, and therefore he himſelfe deliberates and takes the beſt guides he can, or he who out of the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derce of his own abilities or other exteriour aſſiſtances, ſpeaks what ever comes uppermoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>6</label> And here I have the advice and councell of a very wiſe man, no leſſe than <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God, for God is in heaven and thou upon earth, therefore, let thy words be few.</hi> The conſideration of the vaſt diſtance between God and us, Heaven and Earth, ſhould create ſuch apprehenſions in us, that the very beſt and choyceſt of our offertoryes are not acceptable but by Gods gracious vouchſafeing and condeſcenſion: and therefore ſince we are ſo much indebted to God for accepting our beſt, it is not ſafe ventured to preſent him with a dowbaked ſacrifice, and put him off with that which in nature and humane conſideration is abſolutely the worſt; for ſuch is all the crude and imperfect utterance of our more imperfect conceptions. But let <hi>Solomons</hi> reaſon be what it will, good we are ſure it is. Let us conſider who keeps the precept beſt; He that delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, or he that conſiders not but when he ſpeakes: What man in the world is haſty <hi>to offer any thing before God,</hi> if he bee not who prayes <hi>ex tempore?</hi> And then adde to it but the weight of <hi>Solomons</hi> reaſon, and let any man anſwer me if he thinks it can well ſtand with that reverence we owe to the Immenſe, the infinite, and to the eternall God, the God of wiſdome, to offer him a ſacrifice which we durſt not preſent to a Prince, or a prudent Governour in <hi>re ſeriâ,</hi> ſuch as our prayers ought to be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>7</label> And that this may not be daſhed with a pretence it is carnall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115793:4"/>reaſoning I deſire it may be remembred, that it is the argument God himſelfe uſes againſt lame, maimed, and imperfect ſacrifices, <hi>Goe and offer this to thy Prince,</hi> ſee if he will accept it: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that the beſt perſon is to have the beſt preſent; and what the Prince will ſlight as truly unworthy of him, much more is it unfit for God. For God accepts not of any thing we give or doe, as if he were bettred by it: for therefore its eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate is not taken by its relation or naturall complacency to him, it is all alike to him, for in it ſelfe it is to him as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. But God accepts it by its proportion, and commenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to us. That which we call our beſt, and is truly ſo in humane eſtimate, that pleaſes God, for it declares that if we had better, we would give it him. But to reſerve the beſt, ſayes too plainly, that we think any thing is good enough for him. As therefore God in the Law would not be ſerved by that which was imperfect in <hi>genere naturae:</hi> ſo neither now nor ever will that pleaſe him which is imperfect in <hi>geuere morum,</hi> or <hi>materiâ intellectuali,</hi> when we can give a better.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>8</label> Well then, in the nature of the thing, <hi>ex tempore</hi> forms have much the worſe of it. But it is pretended that there is ſuch a thing as the gift of Prayer, a praying with the Spirit, <hi>Et neſcit tarda molimina ſpiritus ſancti gratia.</hi> Gods Spirit (if he pleaſes) can doe his work as well in an inſtant, as in long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation. And to this purpoſe are pretended thoſe places of Scripture which ſpeak of the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit in our prayers, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>And I will poure upon the houſe of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>and the inhabitants of Jeruſalem, the ſpirit of grace and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi> But eſpecially <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Likewiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities; for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelfe maketh interceſſion for us with groanings that cannot be uttered, &amp;c.</hi> From whence the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion that is inferred is in the words of Saint <hi>Paul, That we muſt pray with the ſpirit,</hi> therefore not with ſet forms, therefore <hi>ex tempore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>9</label> The Collection is ſomewhat wild; for there is great inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence in the ſeverall parts, and much more is in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, then was virtually in the premiſes. But ſuch as it is, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115793:4"/>Authors of it I ſuppoſe will own it. And therefore we will examine the maine deſign of it, and then conſider the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar meanes of its perſwaſion, quoted in the objection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>10</label> It is one of the priviledges of the Goſpel, and the benefit of Chriſts aſcenſion, that the holy Ghoſt is given unto the Church, and is become to us the fountaine of gifts and graces. But theſe gifts and graces are improvements and helps of our naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, of our art and induſtry, not extraordinary, miraculous, and immediate infuſions of habits and gifts. That without Gods Spirit we cannot pray aright; that our infirmities need his help; that we know not what to ask of our ſelves, is moſt true: and if ever any Heretique was more confident of his own naturals, or did ever more undervalue Gods grace then ever the <hi>Pelagians</hi> did, yet he denyes not this. But what then? Therefore without ſtudy, without art, without premeditation, without learning, the ſpirit gives the gift of prayer, and it is his grace, that without any naturall or artificiall help makes us pray <hi>ex tempore?</hi> No ſuch thing: The Objection proves nothing of this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>11</label> Here therefore we will joyn iſſue, whether the gifts and helps of the Spirit be immediate infuſions of the Faculties, and powers, and perfect abilities? Or that he doth aſſiſt us only by his aydes externall and internall, in the uſe of ſuch means which God and nature hath given to man, to ennoble his ſoul, better his Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to improve his underſtanding? That the aydes of the holy Ghoſt are only aſſiſtances to us in the uſe of naturall and artificiall means, I will undertake to prove, and from thence it will evidently follow, that labour, and hard ſtudy, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation will ſooneſt purchaſe the gift of prayer, and aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us of the aſſiſtance of the ſpirit; and therefore ſet forms of prayer, ſtudyed and conſidered of are in a true and proper ſenſe, and without enthuſiaſm, the fruits of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>12</label> 1. Gods Spirit did aſſiſt the Apoſtles by wayes extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and fit for the firſt inſtitution of Chriſtianity: but doth aſſiſt us row by the expreſſes of thoſe firſt aſſiſtances which he gave to them immediately. So that the holy Ghoſt is the author of cur ſaith, and we believe with the ſpirit (it is Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115793:5"/>and yet our beliefe comes by hearing and reading the holy Scriptures and their interpretations. Now reconcile theſe two together, Faith comes by hearing, and yet is the gift of the Spirit, and it ſayes, that the gifts of the Spirit are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies, and immediate infuſions of habits, but helps from God to enable us upon the uſe of the meanes of his own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to believe, to ſpeak, to underſtand, to prophecy, and to pray.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>13</label> 2. And that theſe are for this reaſon called gifts, and graces, and iſſues of the Spirit, is ſo evident and notorious, that the ſpeaking of an ordinary revealed truth, is called in Scripture <hi>a ſpeaking by the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Act. 19.21. Act. 16.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> 1 Cor. 12.8. <hi>No man can ſay that Jeſut is the Lord, but by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> For if the holy Ghoſt ſupplyes us with materials, and fundamentals for our building, it is then enough to denominate the whole edifice to be of him, although the labour and the workmanſhip be ours, upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtock. And this is it which the Apoſtles ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Which things alſo we ſpeak, not in the words which mans wiſdome teacheth, but which the holy Ghoſt teacheth, comparing ſpirituall things with ſpirituall.</hi> The holy Ghoſt teaches, yet it is upon our co-operation, our ſtudy and endeavour, while we compare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall; the holy Ghoſt is ſaid to teach us, becauſe theſe ſpirituals were of his ſuggeſtion and revelation.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>14</label> 3. For it is a rule of the Schools, and there is much reaſon in it. <hi>Habitus infuſi infunduntur per modum acquiſitorum,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is infuſed into us, is in the ſame manner infuſed as other things are acquired, that is, ſtep by ſtep, by humane meanes and co-operation, and grace does not give us new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and create another nature, but meliorates and improves our own. And what S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in the Reſurrection, is alſo true in this Queſtion, <hi>That is not firſt which is ſpirituall, but that which is naturall, and then that which is ſpirituall.</hi> The graces and gifts of the Spirit are poſtnate, and are additions to art and nature. God directs our councels, opens our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, regulates our will, orders our affections, ſupplies us with Objects, and Arguments, and opportunities, and revelations <hi>in ſcriptis,</hi> and then moſt when we moſt imploy our own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115793:5"/>God loving to bleſſe all the meanes, and inſtruments of his ſervice, whether they be naturall or acquiſite.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>15</label> But whoſoever ſhall look for any other gifts of the ſpirit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the parts of nature helped by induſtry and Gods bleſſing upon it, and the revelations or the ſuppplyes of matter in holy Scripture, will be very farre to ſeek, having neither reaſon, promiſe, nor experience of his ſide. For why ſhould the ſpirit of Prayer be any other than as the gift and ſpirit of faith (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13) acquired by humane meanes uſing divine aids? that is, by our endeavours in hearing, reading, Catechizing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to obey, and all this bleſſed and promoted by God, this produces faith. And if the ſpirit of Prayer be of greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and hath a promiſe of a ſpeciall prerogative, let the firſt be proved, and the ſecond be ſhewn in any good record, and then I will believe it too.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>16</label> 4. And the parallel of this Argument I the rather urge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I find praying in the holy Ghoſt joyned with graces, which are as much Gods gifts and productions of the ſpirit as any thing in the world, and yet which the Apoſtle preſſes upon us as duties and things put into our power, and to be improved by our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and thoſe are faith (in which I before inſtanced) and charity, <hi>Epiſt. Jud. ver.</hi> 20. <hi>But ye (beloved) building up your ſelves on your most holy Faith, praying in the holy Ghoſt, keep your ſelves in the love of God.</hi> All of the ſame conſideration, Faith, and Prayer and Charity, all gifts of the Spirit, and yet build up your ſelves in faith, and keep yourſelves in love, and therefore by a parity of reaſon, improve your ſelves in the ſpirit of prayer, that is, God by his Spirit having ſupplyed us with matter, let our induſtry and co-operations <hi>per modum naturae,</hi> improve theſe gifts, and build upon this foundation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>17</label> So that in effect, praying in the holy Ghoſt or with the Spirit, is nothing but prayer for ſuch things and in ſuch manner which God by his Spirit hath taught us in holy Scripture. Holy prayers, ſpirituall ſongs, ſo the Apoſtle calls one part of prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſticall or thankſgiving, that is, prayers or ſongs which are ſpirituall <hi>in materiâ.</hi> And if they be called ſpirituall for the efficient cauſe too, the holy Ghoſt being the Author of them, it comes all to one, for therefore he is the cauſe and giver of them,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115793:6"/>becauſe he hath in his word revealed, what things we are to pray for, and there alſo hath taught us the manner.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>18</label> And this is exactly the Doctrine I plainly gather from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected words of Saint <hi>Paul, (The ſpirit helpeth our infirmities)</hi> How ſo? it followes immediately, <hi>For we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought:</hi> So that therefore he is the Spirit of ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and prayer, becauſe he teaches us what to ask, and how to pray, ſo he helps our infirmities, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is in the Greek <hi>Collaborantem adjuvat.</hi> It is an ingeminate expreſſion of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping us in our labours together with him. Now he that ſhall ſay this is not ſufficiently done by Gods Spirit in Scripture by Prayers, and Pſalmes, and Hymnes, and Spirituall Songs, and precepts concerning prayer, ſet down in that holy repoſitory of truth and devotion, undervalues that ineſtimable treaſure of the Spirit; and if it be ſufficiently done there, he that will multiply his hopes farther, then what is ſufficient, may poſſibly deceive himſelf, but never deceive God, and make him multiply and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue miracles, to juſtifie his fancy.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>19</label> 5. Better it is to follow the Scriptures for our guide, as in all things elſe, ſo in this particular, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17, 18. <hi>Take the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God. Praying alwayes with all prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit.</hi> The Word of God is the ſword of the Spirit; praying in the Spirit is one way of uſing it, indeed the only way that he here ſpecifies. Praying in the Spirit then being the uſing of this Sword, and this Sword being the Word of God, it followes evidently, that praying in the Spirit, is praying in or according to the Word of God, that is, in the directions, rules and expreſſes of the Word of God, that is, of the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>20</label> The ſumme is this. Whatſoever this gift is, or this ſpirit of Prayer, it is to be acquired by humane induſtry, by learning of the Scriptures, by reading, by conference, and by whatſoever elſe faculties are improved, and habits enlarged. Gods Spirit hath done his work ſufficiently this way, and he loves not either in nature or grace (which are his two great ſanctions) to multiply miracles when there is no need.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>21</label> 6. So that now I demand, Whether or no, ſince the expiration of the Age of Miracles, does not Gods Spirit moſt aſſiſt us, when
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115793:6"/>we moſt endeavour and moſt uſe the meanes? He that ſayes, No, diſcourages all men from reading the Scriptures, from induſtry, from meditation, from conference, from humane Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and from whatſoever elſe God and good Lawes provoke us to by propoſition of rewards: But if, Yea, (as moſt certainly God will beſt crown the beſt endeavours) then the ſpirit of Prayer is greateſt in him, who (ſuppoſing the like capacities and opportunities) ſtudies hardeſt, reads moſt, practices moſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, deliberates moſt prudently; and then by how much want of meanes is worſe then the uſe of meanes, by ſo much <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> Prayers are worſe then deliberate and ſtudyed. Excellent therefore is the councell of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep. Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God,</hi> (not lightly then and inconſiderately) <hi>If any man miniſter, let him doe it as of the ability which God giveth:</hi> (great reaſon then to put all his abilities and faculties to it) and whether of the two does moſt likely doe that, he that takes paines, and conſiders, and diſcuſſes, and ſo approves and practiſes a form, or he that never conſiders what he ſayes, till hee ſayes it, needs not much deliberation to paſſe a ſentence.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>22</label> 7. Laſtly, did not the Penmen of the Scripture, write the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles and Goſpels reſpectively all by the Spirit? Moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, holy men of God <hi>ſpoke as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> And certainly they were moved by a more immediate motion, and a motion nearer to an Enthuſiaſme, then now adayes in the gift and ſpirit of Prayer. And yet in the midſt of thoſe great aſſiſtances and motions they did uſe ſtudy, art, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and humane abilities. This is more then probable in the different ſtyles of the ſeverall Books, ſome being of admirable art, others lower and plaine. The words were their own, at leaſt ſometimes, not the holy Ghoſts. And if the Fathers and Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians were not deceived by falſe Copies, but that they truly did obſerve, ſometimes to be propriety of expreſſion in the language, ſometimes not true Greek, who will think thoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>routs or imperfections in Grammar, were (in reſpect of the words I ſay preciſely) immediate inſpirations and dictates of the holy Ghoſt, and not rather their own productions of induſtry and humanity? But clearely ſome of their words were the words
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115793:7"/>of <hi>Aratus,</hi> ſome of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> ſome of <hi>Menander,</hi> ſome of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> [<hi>This ſpeak I, not the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.] and yet becauſe the holy Ghoſt renewed their memory, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved their underſtanding, ſupplyed to ſome their want of humane learning, and ſo aſſiſted them that they ſhould not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit an errour in fact or opinion, neither in the narrative nor dogmaticall parts, therefore they writ by the Spirit. Since then we cannot pretend upon any grounds of probability to an inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſo immediate as theirs, and yet their aſſiſtances which they had from the Spirit did not exclude humane arts, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, but that the ableſt Scholler did write the beſt, much rather is this true in the gifts and aſſiſtances we receive, and particularly in the gift of Prayer, it is not an <hi>ex tempore</hi> and an inſpired fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, but the faculties of nature and the abilities of art and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry are improved and ennobled by the ſupervening aſſiſtances of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>23</label> And now let us take a man that pretends he hath the gift of Prayer, and loves to pray <hi>ex tempore,</hi> I ſuppoſe his thoughts goe a little before his tongue; I demand then, Whether cannot this man, when it is once come into his head, hold his tongue, and write down what he hath conceived? If his firſt conceptions were of God and Gods Spirit, then they are ſo ſtill, even when they are written. Or is the Spirit departed from him, upon the ſight of a pen and Ink-horn? It did uſe to be otherwiſe among the old and new Prophets, whether they were Prophets of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or of ordinary Miniſtery. But if his conception may be written, and being written is ſtill a production of the Spirit, then it follows that ſet-forms of Prayer deliberate and deſcribed, may as well be a praying with the Spirit, as ſudden forms and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore</hi> out lets.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>24</label> Now the caſe being thus put, I would faine know what the difference is between deliberate and <hi>ex tempore</hi> Prayers, ſave only that in theſe there is leſſe conſideration and prudence; for that the other are (at leaſt as much as them) the productions of the Spirit, is evident in the very caſe put in this very Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and whether to conſider and to weigh them, be any diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to our devotions, I leave it to all wiſe men to determine. So that in effect, ſince after the pretended aſſiſtance of the Spirit
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115793:7"/>in our Prayers, we may write them down, conſider them, try the ſpirits, and ponder the manner, the reaſon and the religion of the addreſſe; let the world judge whether this ſudden ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance and <hi>ex tempore</hi> forms be any thing elſe, but a direct re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution not to conſider before-hand what we ſpeak.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>25</label> But let us look a little further into the myſtery, and ſee what is meant in Scripture by <hi>praying with the Spirit.</hi> In what ſenſe the holy Ghoſt is called the <hi>ſpirit of Prayer,</hi> I have already ſhewn, <hi>viz.</hi> by the ſame reaſon, as he is the <hi>ſpirit of faith,</hi> of <hi>prudence,</hi> of <hi>knowledge,</hi> of <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and the like. But <hi>praying with the ſpirit</hi> hath beſides this other ſenſes alſo in Scripture. I finde in one place, that then we pray with the Spirit, when the holy Ghoſt does actually excite us to deſires and earneſt tendencies to the obtaining our holy purpoſes, when he gives us zeale and devotion, charity and fervour, ſpirituall violence and holy impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. This ſenſe is alſo in the latter part of the objected words of Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>The Spirit it ſelfe maketh interceſsion for us with groanings, &amp;c.</hi> Indeed this is truly a praying in the ſpirit; but this will doe our reverend Brethren of the Aſſembly little advantage as to the preſent Queſtion. For this ſpirit is not a ſpirit of utterance; not at all clamorous in the eares of the people, but cryes loud in the eares of God with <hi>[groanes unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable]</hi> ſo it followes, and only <hi>[He that ſearcheth the heart, he underſtandeth the meaning of the ſpirit.]</hi> This is the ſpirit of the Son, which God hath ſent into our hearts, (not into our tongues) whereby we cry, <hi>Abba,</hi> Father, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. And this is the great <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for mentall Prayer, which is properly and truly praying by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>26</label> Another praying with the Spirit I find in that place of S <hi>Paul,</hi> from whence this expreſſion is taken, and commonly uſed, <hi>I will pray with the ſpirit, and I will pray with the understanding alſo.</hi> Here they are oppoſed, or at leaſt declared to be things ſeverall and diſparate: where by the way obſerve, that praying with the ſpirit, even in ſenſe of Scripture, is not alwayes moſt to edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people. Not alwayes with underſtanding. And when theſe two are ſeparated, St <hi>Paul</hi> prefers five words with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, before ten thouſand in the ſpirit. For this praying with the ſpirit was indeed then a gift extraordinary and miraculous,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115793:8"/>like as prophecying with the ſpirit, and expired with it. But while it did laſt, it was the loweſt of gifts, <hi>Inter dona linguarum,</hi> it was but a gift of the tongue, and not to be the benefit of the Church directly or immediately.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>27</label> By the way only. If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did ſo undervalve the praying with the Spirit, that he preferred edifying the Church a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand degrees beyond it. I ſuppoſe he would have been of the ſame mind, if this Queſtion had been between praying with the Spirit and obeying our ſuperiors, as he was when it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween praying with the Spirit and edification of the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (if I be not miſtaken) it is matter of great concernment towards the edification of the Church to obey our ſuperiours, not to innovate in publick formes of worſhip, eſpecially with the ſcandall and offence of very wiſe and learned men, and to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the dead Martyrs, who ſealed our Liturgy with their blood.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>28</label> But to return. In this place praying with the Spirit, is no more then my ſpirit praying. For ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> joynes them as terms identicall, and expreſſive one of anothers meaning, as you may pleaſe to read <hi>ver.</hi> 14. and 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and my Spirit truly prayeth.</hi> It is the act of our inner man, praying holy and ſpirituall Prayers. But then indeed at that time there was ſomething extraordinary joyned, for it was in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue, the practice of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> there diſlikes. This alſo will be to none of their purpoſes. For whether it were <hi>ex tempore,</hi> or by premeditation, is not here expreſſed; or if it had, yet that aſſiſtance extraordinary in prayer, if there was any beſide the gift of tongues (which I much doubt) is no more tranſmitted to us, then the ſpeaking tongues in the ſpirit, or prophecyring <hi>ex tempore</hi> and by the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>29</label> But I would adde alſo one experiment which S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo there addes by way of inſtance. If praying with the ſpirit in this place be praying <hi>ex tempore,</hi> then ſo is ſinging too. For they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the ſame place, in the ſame manner, to the ſame end, and I know to reaſon why there ſhould be differing ſenſes put upon them to ſerve purpoſes. And now let us have ſome Church-muſick too, though the Organs be pulled down, and let any the beſt Pſalmiſt of them all, compoſe a hymne in metricall forme,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115793:8"/>and ſing it to a new tune with perfect and true muſick, and all this <hi>ex tempore.</hi> For all this the holy Ghoſt can doe if he pleaſes. But if it be ſaid that the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Chriſtians compoſed their ſongs and hymnes according to art and rules of muſick, by ſtudy and induſtry, and that to this they were aſſiſted by the Spirit; and that this together with the devotion of their ſpirit, was ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the ſpirit, then ſay I, ſo compoſing ſet forms of Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy by skill and prudence, and humane induſtry, may be as much praying with the ſpirit as the other is ſinging with the ſpirit. Plainly enough. In all the ſenſes of praying with the ſpirit, and in all its acceptations in Scripture, to pray or ſing with the ſpirit, neither of them of neceſſity implyes <hi>ex tempore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>30</label> The ſumme or <hi>Collecta</hi> of the premiſes is this, Praying with the ſpirit, is either when the ſpirit ſtirres up our deſires to pray, <hi>Per motionem actualis auxilii,</hi> or when the ſpirit teaches us what, or how to pray, telling us the matter, and manner of our prayers. Or laſtly, dictating the very words of our prayers. There is no other way in the world to pray with the ſpirit, or in the holy Ghoſt, that is pertinent to this Queſtion. And of this laſt manner the Scripture determines nothing, nor ſpeaks any thing expreſſely of it, and yet ſuppoſe it had, we are certaine the holy Ghoſt hath ſupplyed us with all theſe, and yet in ſet formes of prayer beſt of all, I meane there where a difference can be. For as for the deſires, and actuall motions or incitements to pray, they are indifferent to one or the other, to ſet-forms or to <hi>ex tempore.</hi> 2. But as to the matter and manner of prayer, it is clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the expreſſes, and ſet forms of Scriptures, and it is ſupplyed to us by the ſpirit, for he is the great Dictaror of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>31</label> Now then for the very words. No man can aſſure me that the words of his <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayer are the words of the holy Spirit: it is not reaſon nor modeſty to expect ſuch immediate aſſiſtances to ſo little purpoſe, he having ſupplyed us with abilities more then enough to expreſſe our deſires <hi>aliunde,</hi> otherwiſe then by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate dictate. But if we will take <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalter, or the other hymnes of holy Scripture, or any of the Prayers which are reſperſed over the Bible, we are ſure enough that they are the words of Gods Spirit, mediately or immediately, by way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion or extaſie, by viſion, or at leaſt by ordinary aſſiſtance. And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115793:9"/>now then, what greater confidence can any man have for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his Prayer, and the probability of their being accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then when he prayes his Pſalter, or the Lords Prayer, or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther office which he finds conſigned in Scripture? When Gods Spirit ſtirs us up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o an actuall devotion, and then we uſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee hath deſcribed and taught, and the very words which Chriſt, and Chriſts Spirit, and the Apoſtles, and other perſons full of the holy Ghoſt did uſe; if in the world there be any praying with the Spirit, (I mean in vocall prayer) this is it.</p>
            <p>And thus I have examined the intire and full ſcope of this Queſtion, and rifled their Objection. Now I ſhall proceed to ſome few Arguments which are more extrinſecall to the nature of the thing.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>32</label> It is a practice prevailing among thoſe of our Brethren that are zealous for <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayers, to pray their Sermons over, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their doctrine into Devotion and Lyturgy. I miſlike it not for the thing it ſelfe, if it were done regularly for the manner, and the matter were alwayes pious and true. But who ſhall aſſure me when the preacher hath diſputed, or rather dogmatically decreed a point of predeſtination, or of preſcience, of contingency, or of liberty, or any of the moſt myſterious parts of Divinity, and then prayes his Sermon over, that he then prayes with the Spirit? Unleſſe I be ſure that he alſo preached with the Spirit, I cannot be ſure that he prayes with the ſpirit, for all he prayes <hi>ex tempore.</hi> Nay, if I heare a Proteſtant preach in the morning, and an Anabaptiſt in the afternoone, to day a Presbyterian, to morrow an Independent, am I not moſt ſure that when they have preached Contradictories, and all of them pray their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons over, that they doe not all pray with the ſpirit? More than one in this caſe cannot pray with the ſpirit, poſſibly all may pray againſt him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>33</label> 2. From whence I thus argue in behalſe of ſet forms of prayer. That in the caſe above put, how ſhall I or any man elſe ſay Amen to their prayers that preach and pray contradictories? At leaſt I am much hindred in my devotion. For beſides that, it derives our opinions into our devotions, makes every ſchoole point become our religion, and makes God a party, (ſo farre as we can) intitling him to our impertinent wranglings. Beſides
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115793:9"/>this, I ſay, while we ſhould attend to our addreſſes towards God, we are to conſider whether the point be true or no, and by that time we have tacitly diſcourſed it, we are upon another point which alſo perhaps is as Queſtionable as the former, and by this time our ſpirit of devotion is a little diſcompoſed and ſomething out of countenance, there is ſo much other imployment for the ſpirit, the ſpirit of diſcerning and judging. All which inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences are avoyded in ſet formes of Liturgy. For we know be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand the conditions of our Communion, and to what we are to ſay Amen, to which if we like it we may repaire; if not, there is no harm done; your devotion ſhall not be ſurprized, nor your Communion invaded, as it may be and often is in your <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayers. And this thing hath another collaterall inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, which is of great conſideration; for upon what confidence can we ſollicite any Recuſants to come to our Church, where we cannot promiſe them that the devotions there to be uſed, ſhall be innocent, nor can we put him into a condition to judge for himſelfe? If hee will venture he may, but we can uſe no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make him chooſe our Churches, though he ſhould quit his own.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>34</label> 3. But again, let us conſider with ſobriety. Are not thoſe prayers and hymnes in holy Scripture, excellent compoſitions, admirable inſtruments of devotion, full of piety, rare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable addreſſes to God? Dare any man with his gift of prayer pretend, that he can <hi>ex tempore</hi> or by ſtudy make better? Who dares pretend that he hath a better ſpirit then <hi>David</hi> had, or then the Apoſtles and Prophets, and other holy perſons in Scripture, whoſe Prayers and Pſalmes are by Gods Spirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to the uſe of the Church for ever? Or will it be denyed but that they alſo are excellent directories and patterns for prayer? And if patterns, the nearer we draw to our example, are not the imitations and repreſentments the better? And what then if we took the ſamplers themſelves, is there any imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in them, and can we mend them and correct <hi>Magnificat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>35</label> In a juſt porportion and commenſuration, I argue ſo concerning the primitive and ancient forms of Church ſervice, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed according to thoſe ſo excellent patterns, which if they had remained pure as in their firſt inſtitution, or had alwayes been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115793:10"/>as they have been reformed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they would againſt all defiance put in for the next place to thoſe formes or Liturgy which <hi>Mutatis mutandis</hi> are nothing but the Words of Scripture. But I am reſolved at this preſent not to enter into Queſtion concerning the matter of prayers. But for the forme this I ſay further.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>36</label> 4. That the Church of God hath the promiſe of the ſpirit made to her in generall, to her in her Catholick and united ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, to the whole Church firſt, then to particular Churches, then in the loweſt ſeat of the Category to ſingle perſons. Now then I infer, if any ſingle perſons will have us to believe without all poſſibility of proofe (for ſo it muſt be) that they pray with the Spirit, (for how ſhall they be able to prove the ſpirit actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to abide in thoſe ſingle perſons) then much rather muſt we believe it of the Church, which by how much the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall it is, ſo much the more of the ſpirit ſhe is likely to have; and then if there be no errours in the matter, the Church hath the advantage and probability on her ſide, and if there be an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in matter in either of them, they faile of their pretences, neither of them have the ſpirit. But the publick ſpirit in all reaſon is to be truſted before the private, when there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, the Church being <hi>Prior &amp; potior in promiſſis,</hi> ſhe hath a greater and <hi>prior</hi> title to the ſpirit. And why the Church hath not the ſpirit of prayer in her compoſitions as well as any of her children, I deſire once for all to be ſatisfied upon true grounds either of reaſon or revelation.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>37</label> 5. Or if the Church ſhall be admitted to have the gift, and the ſpirit of prayer given unto her by virtue of the great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the ſpirit, to abide with her for ever, yet for all this ſhe is taught to pray in a ſet form of prayer, and yet by the ſpirit too. For what think we? When Chriſt taught us to pray in that incomparable modell, the Lords Prayer, if we pray that prayer devoutly, and with pious and actuall intention, doe we not pray in the Spirit of Chriſt, as much as if we prayed any other form of words pretended to be taught us by the Spirit? Wee are ſure that Chriſt and Chriſts Spirit taught us this Prayer; they only gather by conjectures and opinions, that in their <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> forms the ſpirit of Chriſt teaches them. So much then as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115793:10"/>certainties are better then uncertaines, and God above man, ſo much is this ſet form (beſides the infinite advantages in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) better then their <hi>ex tempore</hi> forms in the form it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>38</label> 6. If I ſhould deſcend to minutes and particulars, I could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the behalfe of ſet forms, that God preſcribed to <hi>Moſes</hi> a ſet form of prayer and benediction to be uſed when he did bleſſe the people. 7. That <hi>Moſes</hi> compoſed a ſong or hymne for the children of Iſrael to uſe to all their generations. 8. That <hi>David</hi> compoſed many for the ſervice of the tabernacle. 9. That <hi>Solomon</hi> and the holy Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> brought them in and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued them in the miniſtration of the temple. 10. That all Scripture is written for our learning, and ſince all theſe and many more ſet forms of prayer are left there upon record, it is more then probable that they were left there for our uſe and devotion. 11. That S. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt taught his Diſciples a forme of prayer. 12. And that Chriſts Diſciples begged the ſame favour, and it was granted as they deſired it. 13. And that Chriſt gave it not only <hi>in maſſâ materiae,</hi> but <hi>in forma verborum;</hi> not in a confuſed heap of matter, but in an exact compoſure of words, it makes it evident, he intended it not only <hi>pro regula petendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> for a direction of what things we are to ask, but alſo <hi>pro forma orationis,</hi> for a ſet form of Prayer. In which alſo I am moſt certainly confirmed (beſides the univerſall teſtimony of Gods Church ſo atteſting it) in the precept which Chriſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>When ye pray, pray after this manner:</hi> and indeed it points not the matter only of our prayers, but the form of it, the manner and the matter of the addreſſe both. But in the repetition of it by Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> the preceptive words ſeeme to limit us, and direct us to this very form of words, <hi>When ye pray, ſay, Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> 14. I could alſo adde the example of all the Jewes, and by conſequence of our bleſſed Saviour, who ſung a great part of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalter in their feaſt of Paſſeover, which part is called by the Iewes the great <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> it begins at the 113 Pſalm, and ends at the 118 incluſively. And the Scripture mentions it as part of our bleſſed Saviours devotion, and of his Diſciples, that they ſung a Pſalme. 15. That this afterward became a Precept Evangelicall, that we ſhould praiſe God in Hymnes, Pſalmes, and ſpirituall Songs, which is a form of Liturgy, in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115793:11"/>which we ſing with the ſpirit, but yet cannot make our Hymnes <hi>ex tempore,</hi> (it would be wild ſtuffe if we ſhould goe about it.) 16. And laſtly, that a ſet form of worſhip and addreſſe to God was recorded by Saint <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 15.</note> and ſung in heaven, and it was compoſed out of the ſongs of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (<hi>Exod.</hi> 15.) of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 145.) and of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> (<hi>Chap.</hi> 10.6, 7.) which certainly is a very good precedent for us to imitate, although but revealed to Saint <hi>John</hi> by way of viſion and extaſie. All which and many more are to me as ſo many Arguments of the uſe, excellency, and neceſſity of ſet forms of Prayer for publick Liturgies, and of greateſt conveniencie, even for private devotions.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>39</label> 17. And ſo the Church of God in all Ages did underſtand it. I ſhall not multiply Authorities to this purpoſe, for they are too many and various; but ſhall only obſerve two great inſtances of their beliefe and practiſe in this particular. 1. The one is the perpetuall uſe and great Eulogies of the Lords Prayer, aſſiſted by the many Commentaries of the Fathers upon it. 2. The other is that ſolemn form of benediction and myſticall prayer (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls it, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Trinit. c.</hi> 4.) which all Churches (and themſelves ſaid it was by Ordinance Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call) uſed in the Conſecration of the bleſſed Sacrament. But all of them uſed the Lords Prayer in the Canon, and office of Conſecration, and other prayers taken from Scripture, (ſo <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> teſtifies, that the Conſecration is made <hi>per preces verbi Dei,</hi> by the prayers taken from the Word of God) and the whole Canon was ſhort, determined and myſterious.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>40</label> Who deſires to be further ſatisfied in this particular, ſhall find enough in <hi>Walafridus Strabo, Aymonius, Caſſander, Flacius Illyricus, Joſephus Vicecomes,</hi> and the other Ritualiſts, and in the old offices themſelves. So that I need not put you in mind of that famous doxology of <hi>Gloria Patria, &amp;c.</hi> nor the <hi>Triſagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> nor any of thoſe memorable hymnes uſed in the Ancient Church, ſo knownly and frequently, that the beginning of them came to bee their name, and they were known more by their own words, then the Authors inſcription.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>41</label> At laſt when ſome men that thought themſelves better gifted would be venturing at conceived formes of their own, there was a timely reſtraint made in the Councell of <hi>Milevis</hi> in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115793:11"/>
               <hi>Africa, Placuit ut preces quae probatae fuerint in Concilio ab omnibus celebrentur, nec aliae omnino dicantur in Eccleſia, niſi quae à pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioribus factae fuerint in Synodo.</hi> That's the reſtraint and prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, publick prayers muſt be ſuch as are publickly appointed, and preſcribed by our Superiours; and no private forms of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving muſt be uſed in the Church. The reaſon followes, <hi>Ne forte aliquid contra fidem, vel per ignorantiam, vel per minus ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſit compoſitum:</hi> Leſt through ignorance or want of delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any thing be ſpoken in our prayers againſt faith [and good manners.] The reaſon is good, and they are eare-witneſſes of it that hear the variety of prayers before and after Sermons, there, where the Directory is practiſed, where (to ſpeak moſt modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) not only their private opinions, but alſo humane intereſts, and their own perſonall concernments, and wild fancies, born per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not two dayes before, are made the objects of the peoples hopes, of their deſires, and their prayers, and all in the meane time pretend to the holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>42</label> I will not now inſtance in the vaine-glory that is appendant to theſe <hi>ex tempore</hi> formes of prayer, where the gift of the man is more then the devotion of the man: nor will I conſider that then his gift is beſt, when his prayer is longeſt: and if he take a complacency in his gift (as who is not apt to doe it?) he will be ſure to extend his Prayer, till a ſuſpicious and ſcrupulous man would be apt to ſay, his prayer preſſed hard upon that which our bleſſed Saviour reprehended in the Phariſees, who thought to bee heard for their much babling. But theſe things are accidentall to the nature of the thing. And therefore though they are too certainly conſequent to the perſon, yet I will not be too ſevere, but preſerve my ſelfe on the ſurer ſide of charitable conſtruction, which truly I deſire to keep, nor only to their perſons whom I much reverence, but alſo to their actions. But yet I durſt not doe the ſame thing, even for theſe laſt reaſons, though I had no other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>43</label> But it is objected, that in ſet forms of Prayer, we reſtrain and confine the bleſſed Spirit; and in conceived forms, when every man is left to his liberty, then the Spirit is free, unlimited and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtra ned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>44</label> I anſwer, either their conceived formes (I uſe their own words,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115793:12"/>though indeed the expreſſion is very inartificiall) are premeditate and deſcribed, or they are <hi>ex tempore.</hi> If they be premeditate and deſcribed, then the Spirit is as much limited in their conceived forms as in the Churches conceived forms. For as to this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, it is all one who deſcribes and limits the form, whether the Church, or a ſingle man does it, ſtill the Spirit is in conſtraint and limit. So that in this caſe they are not angry at ſet forms of Prayer, but that they do not make them. And if it be replyed, that if a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon compoſes a ſet form, he may alter it if he pleaſe, and ſo his ſpirit is at liberty. I anſwer, ſo may the Church, if ſhe ſee cauſe for it: and unleſſe there be cauſe, the ſingle perſon will not alter it, unleſſe he do things unreaſonable, and without cauſe. So that it will be an unequall and a peeviſh quarrell to allow of ſer forms of prayer made by private perſons, and not of ſet forms made by the publick ſpirit of the Church. It is evident, that the Spirit is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited in both alike.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>45</label> But if by <hi>[Conceived forms]</hi> in this objection they meane <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayers (for ſo they moſt generally practice it) and that in the uſe of theſe the liberty of the ſpirit is beſt preſerved. To this I anſwer, that the being <hi>ex tempore</hi> or premeditate will be wholly impertinent to this Queſtion of limiting the ſpirit. For there may be great liberty in ſet forms, even when there is much variety; and there may be great reſtraint in <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayers, even then when it ſhall be called unlawfull to uſe ſet forms. That the ſpirit is reſtrained, or that it is free in either, is acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall to them both; for it may be either free or not free in both as it may happen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>46</label> But the reſtraint is this, that every one is not left to his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to pray how he liſt, (with premeditation or without, it makes not much matter) but that he is preſcribed unto by the ſpirit of another. But if it be a fault thus to reſtraine the ſpirit, I would faine know, is not the ſpirit reſtrained when the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation ſhall be confined to the form of this one mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing? or it ſhall be unlawfull, or at leaſt a diſgrace and diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to uſe any ſet forms, eſpecially of the Churches compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. More plainly thus.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>47</label> 2. Doth not the Miniſter confine and reſtraine the ſpirit of the Lords People, when they are tyed to his form? It would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115793:12"/>ſound of more liberty to their ſpirits, that every one might make a prayer of his own, and all pray together; and not be forced or confined to the Miniſters ſingle dictate, and private ſpirit. It is true, it would breed confuſions, and therefore they might pray ſilently till the Sermon began, and not for the avoiding one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience runne into a greater, and to avoid the diſorder of a popular noyſe reſtraine the bleſſed Spirit; for even in this caſe as well as in the other, <hi>Where the ſpirit of God is, there must be liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>48</label> 3. If the ſpirit muſt be at liberty, who ſhall aſſure us this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty muſt be in forms of prayer? And if ſo, whether alſo it muſt be in publike prayer, and will it not ſuffice that it be in private? And if in publike prayers, is not the liberty of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſufficiently preſerved in that the publike ſpirit is free? That is, the Church hath power upon occaſion to alter and encreaſe her Litanyes. By what Argument ſhall any man make it ſo much as probable, that the holy Ghoſt is injured, if every private Miniſters private ſpirit ſhall be guided (and therefore by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence limited) by the Authority of the Churches publick ſpirit?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>49</label> 4. Does not the Directory that thing which is here called re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining of the ſpirit? Does it not appoint every thing but the words? And after this is it not a goodly <hi>Palladium</hi> that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, and a princely liberty that they leave unto the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to be free only in the ſupplying the place of a Vocabulary and a <hi>Copia Verborum?</hi> For as for the matter, it is all there deſcribed and appointed, and to thoſe determined ſenſes the ſpirit muſt aſſiſt or not at all, only for the words he ſhall take his choyce. Now I deſire it may be conſidered ſadly and ſeriouſly: Is it not as much injury to the ſpirit to reſtraine his matter, as to appoint his words? Which is the more conſiderable of the two, ſenſe or Language, Matter or Words? I meane when they are taken ſingle and ſeparately. For ſo they may very well be (for as if men preſcribe the matter only, the ſpirit may cover it with ſeverall words and expreſſions, ſo if the ſpirit preſcribe the words, I may ſtill abound in variety of ſenſe, and preſerve the liberty of my meaning; we ſee that true in the various in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of the ſame words of Scripture.) So that in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115793:13"/>greater of the two, the Spirit is reſtrained, when his matter is appointed, and to make him amends, for not truſting him with the matter without our directions and limitations, we truſt him to ſay what he pleaſes, ſo it be to our ſenſe, to our purpoſes. A goodly compenſation ſurely!</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>50</label> 5. Did not Chriſt reſtrain the ſpirit of his Apoſtles, when he taught them to pray the Lords Prayer, whether his precept to his Diſciples concerning it, was <hi>Pray this,</hi> or <hi>Pray thus, Pray theſe words,</hi> or <hi>pray after this manner?</hi> or though it had been leſſe then either, and been only a Directory for the matter, ſtill it is a thing which our Brethren in all other caſes of the ſame nature are reſolved perpetually to call a reſtraint. Certainly then this pretended reſtraint, is no ſuch formidable thing. Theſe men themſelves doe it by directing all the matter, and much of the manner, and Chriſt himſelfe did it, by preſcribing both the matter, and the words too.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>51</label> 6. Theſe reſtraints (as they are called) or determinations of the Spirit are made by the Spirit himſelfe. For I demand, when any Aſſembly of Divines appointed the matter of Prayers to all particular Miniſters as this hath done, is that appointment by the Spirit or no? If no, then for ought appears, this Directory not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by Gods Spirit, may be an enemy to it. But if this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment be by the Spirit, then the determination and limitation of the Spirit, is by the Spirit himſelf, and ſuch indeed is every pious and prudent conſtitution of the Church in matters ſpirituall: Such as was that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when he preſcribed orders for publicke prophecying, and interpretation, and ſpeaking with tongues. The ſpirit of ſome he ſo reſtrained, that he bound them to hold their peace, he permitted but two or three to ſpeak at one meeting, the reſt were to keep ſilence, though poſſibly fix or ſeven might at that time have the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>52</label> 7. Is it not a reſtraint of the Spirit to ſing a Pſalm in meeter by appointment? Cleerely as much as appointing formes of prayer or Euchariſt. And yet that we ſee done daily, and no ſcruple made. Is not this to be partiall in judgement, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate of what wee doe?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>53</label> 8. And now after all this ſtrife, what harm is there in reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſpirit in the preſent ſenſe? What prohibition, what law,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115793:13"/>what reaſon or revelation is againſt it? What inconvenience in the nature of the thing? For can any man be ſo weak as to imagine a deſpite is done to the ſpirit of grace, when thoſe gifts to his Church are uſed regularly and by order? As if prudence were no gift of Gods ſpirit, as if helps in Government, and the ordering ſpirituall matters were none of thoſe graces which Chriſt when he aſcended up on high gave unto Men. But this whole matter is wholly a ſtranger to reaſon, and never ſeen in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>54</label> For Divinity never knew any other vitious reſtraining of the Spirit, but either ſuppreſſing thoſe holy incitements to virtue and good life, which Gods Spirit miniſters to us externally or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, or elſe a forbidding by publick Authority the Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments, to ſpeak ſuch truths as God hath commended, and ſo taking away the liberty of Prophecying. The firſt is directly vitious <hi>In materia ſpeciale,</hi> the ſecond is tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Antichriſtian. And to it perſecution of true Religion is to be reduced. But as for this pretended limiting or reſtraining the ſpirit, <hi>viz.</hi> by appointing a regular form of prayer, it is ſo very a Chimera, that it hath no footing or foundation upon any ground where a wiſe man may build his confidence.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>55</label> 9. But laſtly, how if the ſpirit muſt be reſtrained, and that by precept Apoſtolicall? That calls us to a new account. But if it be not true, what meanes S. <hi>Paul,</hi> by ſaying <hi>The ſpirits of the Prophets muſt be ſubject to the Prophets?</hi> What greater reſtraint then ſubjection? If ſubjected, then they muſt be ruled; if ruled, then limited, preſcribed unto, and as much under reſtraint as the ſpirits of the ſuperiour Prophets ſhall judge convenient. I ſuppoſe by this time this objection will trouble us no more. But perhaps another will.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>56</label> For why are not the Miniſters to be left as well to their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in making their Prayers as their Sermons? I anſwer, the Church may if ſhe will, but whether ſhe doth well or no, let her conſider. This I am ſure, there is not the ſame reaſon, and I fear the experience the world hath already had of it, will make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration enough of the inconvenience. But however the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences are many.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>57</label> 1. Our prayers offered up by the Miniſter, are in behalfe and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115793:14"/>in the name of the people, and therefore great reaſon they ſhould know before-hand, what is to be preſented, that if they like not the meſſage, they may refuſe to communicate; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince people are ſo divided in their opinions, in their hopes, and in their faiths: it being a duty to refuſe Communion with thoſe prayers which they think to have in them the matter of ſin or doubting. Which reaſon on the other part ceaſes, for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter being to ſpeak from God to the people, if he ſpeaks what he ought not, God can right himſelfe, however is not partner of the finne, as in the other caſe, the people poſſibly may be.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>58</label> 2. It is more fit a liberty be left in preaching then praying, becauſe the addreſſe of our diſcourſes and exhortations are to be made according to the underſtanding and capacity of the audience, their prejudices are to be removed, all advantages to be taken, and they are to be ſurprized that way they lie moſt open [<hi>But being crafty I caught you,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi>] and diſcourſes and arguments <hi>ad hominem,</hi> upon their particular principles and practices may more move them then the moſt polite and accurate that doe not comply and wind about their fancies and affections. S. <hi>Paul</hi> from the abſurd practice of being baptized for the dead, made an excellent Argument to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>Corinthians</hi> of the Reſurrection. But this reaſon alſo ceaſes in our prayers. For God underſtandeth what we ſay ſure enough, he hath no prejudices to be removed, no infirmities to be wrought upon, and a fine figure of Rhetorick, a pleaſant cadence, and a curious expreſſion, move not him at all; no other twinings and complyances ſtirre him but charity, and humility, and zeale, and importunity, which all are things internall and ſpirituall. And therefore of neceſſity there is to be great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſcourſes to the people, and permiſſions accordingly, but not ſo to God, with whom a <hi>Deus miſerere</hi> prevailes as ſoon as the great office of 40 houres not long ſince invented in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other prayers ſpun out to a length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the extenſion of the office of a Phariſee.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>59</label> 3. I feare it cannot ſtand with our reverence to God, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to every ſpirit a liberty of publike addreſſe to him in behalfe of the people. Indeed he that is not fit to pray, is not alwayes fit to preach; but it is more ſafe to be bold with the people then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115793:14"/>with God, if the perſons be not ſo fit. In that there may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, but there may be impiety and irreligion in this. The people may better excuſe and pardon an indiſcretion or a rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (if any ſuch ſhould happen) then we may venture to offer it to God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>60</label> 4. There is a latitude of Theology, much whereof is left to us, ſo, without preciſe and clear determination, that without breach either of faith or charity, men may differ in opinion: and if they may not be permitted to abound in their own ſenſe, they will be apt to complaine of tyrannie over conſciences, and that men Lord it over their faith. In Prayer this thing is ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that it is imprudent and full of inconvenience to derive ſuch things into our prayers, which may with good profit be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Sermons. Therefore here a liberty may well enough be granted, when there it may better be denyed.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>61</label> 5. But indeed, if I may freely declare my opinion, I think it were not amiſſe if the liberty of making Sermons were ſomething more reſtrained then it is, and that either ſuch perſons only were intruſted with liberty for whom the Church her ſelfe may ſafely bee reſponſall, that is, to men learned and pious, and that the other part, the <hi>Vulgus Cleri,</hi> ſhould inſtruct the people out of the fountaines of the Church, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the publick ſtock, till by ſo long exerciſe and diſcipline in the Schooles of the Prophets, they may alſo be intruſted to miniſter of their own unto the people. This I am ſure was the practice of the Primitive Church when Preaching was as ably and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly performed as now it is. But in this I preſcribe nothing. But truly I think the reverend Divines of the Aſſembly are many of my mind in this particular, and that they obſerve a liberty indulged to ſome perſons to preach, which I think they had rather ſhould hold their peace, and yet think the Church better edified in your ſilence then their Sermons.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>62</label> 6. But yet me thinks the Argument objected, if it were turned with the edge the other way, would have more reaſon in it: and inſtead of arguing <hi>[Why ſhould not the ſame be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in praying as in preaching]</hi> it were better to ſubſtitute this. If they can pray with the ſpirit, why alſo doe they not preach with the ſpirit? and if praying with the ſpirit be praying <hi>ex
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115793:15"/>tempore,</hi> why ſhall they not preach <hi>ex tempore</hi> too, or elſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that they preach without the ſpirit, or that they have not the gift of Preaching? For to ſay that the gift of prayer, is a gift <hi>ex tempore,</hi> but the gift of Preaching is with ſtudy and deliberation, is to become vaine and impertinent. <hi>Quis enim diſcrevit?</hi> Who hath made them of a different conſideration? I mean as to this particular, as to their efficient cauſe. Nor rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor revelation, nor God, nor man.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>63</label> To ſumme up all. If any man hath a mind to exerciſe his gift of Prayer, let him ſet himſelf to work, and compoſe Books of Devotion, (we have great need of them in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo apparent need, that the Papiſts have made it an objection againſt us) and this his gift of Prayer will bee to edification. But otherwiſe, I underſtand it is more fit for oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, then any ſpirituall advantage. For God hears us not the ſooner for our <hi>ex tempore,</hi> long, or conceived prayers; poſſibly they may become a hindrance, as in the caſes before inſtanced. And I am ſure if the people be intelligent, and can diſcern, they are hindred in their Devotion, for they dare not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> till they have conſidered; and many ſuch caſes will occurre in <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayers, that need much conſidering before we atteſt them. But if the people bee not intelligent, they are apt to ſwallow all the inconveniencies which may multiply in ſo great a licence; and therefore it were well that the Governours of the Church who are to anſwer for their ſoules, ſhould judge for them, before they ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> which judgement cannot bee without ſet-forms of Liturgy. My ſentence therefore is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Let us be as we are already. Few changes are for the better.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>64</label> For if it be pretended, that in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was compoſed with much art and judgement by a Church that hath as much reaſon to be confident ſhe hath the Spirit and gifts of Prayer, as any ſingle perſon hath, and each learned man that was at its firſt compoſition, can as much prove that he had the Spirit, as the objectors now adayes: (and he that boaſts moſt, certainly hath the leaſt.) If I ſay it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, there are many errours and inconveniences both in the order and the matter of the Common-Prayer Book, made by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115793:15"/>ſuch men, with ſo much induſtry: How much more, and with how much greater reaſon may we all dread the inconveniencies and diſorders of <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayers? where there is neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of heads, nor premeditation, nor induſtry, nor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, nor art, nor any of thoſe things (or at leaſt not in the ſame degree) which were likely to have exempted the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book from errours and diſorders. If theſe things be in the green tree, what will be done in the dry?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>65</label> But if it be ſaid, the <hi>ex tempore</hi> and conceived prayers will be ſecured from errour by the Directory, becauſe that chalks them out the matter. I anſwer, it is not ſufficient, becauſe if when men ſtudy both the matter and the words too, they may be (and it is pretended are actually) erroneous; much more may they when the matter is leſt much more at liberty, and the words under no reſtraint at all. And no man can avoid the preſſure and the weight of this, unleſſe the Compilers of the Directory were infallible, and that all their followers were ſo too, of the certainty of which I am not yet ſully ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Numb. </seg>66</label> And after all this I would fain know, what benefit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages ſhall the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her united capacity, and every particular in the diffuſed capacity receive by this new device? For the publike it is cleare, that whether the Miniſters pray before they ſtudy; or ſtudy before they pray, there muſt needs be infinite deformity in the publike worſhip, and all the benefits which were before the conſequents of conformity and unity, will be loft, and if they be not valuable, I leave it to all them to conſider, who know the inconveniences of publike diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union, and the publike diſunion that is certainly conſequent to them who doe not communicate in any common formes of worſhip. And to think that the Directory will bring conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is as if one ſhould ſay, that all who are under the ſame He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere are joyned <hi>in communi patriá,</hi> and will love like Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen; for under the Directory there will be as different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, and as different deſires, and as differing formes as there are ſeverall varieties of men and manners under the one halfe of heaven, who yet breath under the ſame halfe of the Globe. But I ask again what benefit can the publike receive by this forme, or this no form, for I know not whether to call it. Shall the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115793:16"/>matter of prayers be better in all Churches? ſhall God be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſerved? ſhall the word of God and the beſt patterns of prayers be alwayes exactly followed? It is well if it be. But there is ſecurity given us by the Directory; for the matter is left at every mans diſpoſe for all that, and we muſt depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the honeſty of every particular for it; and if any man proves a Heretick, or a Knave, then he may introduce what impiety he pleaſe, into the publick formes of Gods worſhip; and there is no law made to prevent it, and it muſt be cured afterwards if it can; but before-hand it is not prevented at all by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory, which truſts every man. But I obſerve, that all the benefit which is pretended, is, that it will make an able Miniſtery, which I confeſſe I am very much from believing, and ſo will every man be that conſiders what kind of men they are that have been moſt zealous for that way of conceived prayer. I am ſure that very few of the learnedſt, very many ignorants, moſt thoſe who have made leaſt abode in the Schools of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. And that I may diſgrace no mans perſon, we ſee Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the moſt illiberall arts, and women pretend to it, and doe it with as many words (and that's the maine thing) with as much confidence, and ſpeciouſneſſe, and ſpirit, as the beſt among them. And it is but a ſmall portion of learning that will ſerve a man to make conceived formes of prayer, which they have eaſily upon the ſtock of other men, or upon their own fancie, or upon any thing in which no learning is required. He that knowes nothing of the craft may be in the Preachers trade. But what? Is God better ſerved? I would faine ſee any Authority, or any reaſon, or any probability for that. I am ſure ignorant men offer him none of the beſt ſacrifices <hi>ex tempore,</hi> and learned men will be ſure to deliberate, and know. God is then better ſerved, when he ſerved by a publike, then when by a private ſpirit. I cannot imagine what accruements will hence come to the publike: it may be ſome advantages may be to the private intereſts of men. For there are a ſort of men whom out bleſſed Saviour noted, who do <hi>devoure widowes houſes, and for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make long prayers.</hi> They make prayers, and they make them long, by this meanes they receive double advantages, for they get reputation to their ability, and to their piety. And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115793:16"/>although the Common-prayer Book in the Preface to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory bee charged with unneceſſary length, yet we ſee that moſt of theſe men, they that are moſt eminent or would be ſo, make their prayers longer, and will not loſe the benefits which their credit gets, and they by their credit, for making their prayers.</p>
            <p>Adde to this that there is no promiſe in Scripture, that he who prayes <hi>ex tempore</hi> ſhall be heard the better, or that he ſhall bee aſſiſted at all to ſuch purpoſes; and therefore to innovate in ſo high a matter without a warrant to command us, or a promiſe to warrant us, is no better then vanity in the thing, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in the perſon. He therefore that conſiders that this way of prayer is without all manner of precedent in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, againſt the example of all famous Churches in all Chriſtendome in the whole deſcent of 15. Ages, without all command and warrant of Scripture, that it is unreaſonable in the nature of the thing, againſt prudence and the beſt wiſedome of humanity, becauſe it is without deliberation, that it is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in a high degree without that Authority which is truly and by inherent and ancient right to command and preſcribe to us in externall forms of worſhip, that it is much to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the firſt reformers of our Religion, that it gives en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the Papiſts, to quarrell with ſome reaſon and more pretence againſt our Reformation, as being by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory confeſſed to have been done in much blindneſſe, and therefore might erre in the exceſſe as well as in the defect, in the throwing out too much, as caſting off too little, which is the more likely, becauſe they wanted zeale to carry it farre enough. He that confiders the univerſall deformity of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip, and the no meanes of union, no Symbol of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like communion being publikely conſigned, that all Hereſies may with the ſame Authority bee brought into our prayers, and offered to God in behalfe of the people, with the ſame Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that any truth may, all the matter of our prayers being left to the choyce of all men, of all perſwaſions, and then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that actually there are in many places, hereſie, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy, and impertinency, and illiterate rudeneſſes put into the devotions of the moſt Solemne dayes, and the moſt publike
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115793:17"/>meetings; and then laſtly, that there are divers parts of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, for which no proviſions at all is made in the Directory, and the very adminiſtration of the Sacraments left ſo looſely, that if there be any thing eſſentiall in the forms of Sacraments, the Sacrament may come ineffectuall by want of due words, and due miniſtration. I ſay, he that conſiders all theſe things (and many more he may conſider) will finde that particular men are not fit to be intruſted to offer in publike with their private ſpirit, to God, for the people, in ſuch ſolemnities, in matters of ſo great concernment, where the honour of God, the benefit of the people, the intereſt of Kingdomes, the being of a Church, the unity of minds, the conformity of practice, the truth of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, and the ſalvation of ſoules, are ſo very much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as they are in the publike prayers of a whole Nationall Church. An unlearned man is not to be truſted, and a wiſe man dare not truſt himſelfe; hee that is ignorant cannot, he that is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will not.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
